When I read the screenplay, the very first
draft of the screenplay, and this is the
Eric Roth screenplay, because there were
many screenplays prior to that that were
done over many years,
I just kept turning the
page to see what was
going to happen next.
It was... I mean, I had no
real desire or compulsion
to make a movie about
a guy with a low IQ.
It seemed to be the right character,
and I kept wanting to know what was going
to happen to this character in this
strange story.
I just kept wanting to know
what was going to happen,
how was this going to end,
what was going to happen.
And whenever you get a
screenplay and that happens, as
crippled as it was very early
on, that's always a good sign.
The Feather always started the movie in
the screenplay.
It wasn't at the end, though.
That we put in later, in later drafts of
the script.
But, you know, the Feather was always this
sort of...
For me, it was this
metaphor for sort of the
randomness of life and
sort of the destiny of life.
I mean, the destiny in that it lands at
Forrest's foot and sort of the randomness
that it could have landed anywhere, like it
almost lands on that other guy's shoulder.
So to me, it was sort
of always a metaphor for
us just sort of floating
around on a breeze.
And I think it's the true nature of the
story of Forrest is that...
And what's wonderful about the tale we're
about to tell is that you really don't
know what direction it's going to take
until it takes it.
You know, I can't imagine any other actor
doing it.
Tom was perfect for this part.
It was something that he really wanted to
do.
I completely trust him.
He didn't show me anything until the day.
I mean, it was, you know, he wasn't
like...
He didn't say, no, Bob, let me show you
the Forrest I'm going to do.
It wasn't a situation like that.
It was all mutual trust.
I knew on the day that he would rise to
the occasion.
We were very fortunate
that, you know, Tom actually
didn't work for the first
couple of weeks of shooting.
I did all this stuff with the little kid.
And then I think Tom just did Vietnam or
something and he did some early Forrest
stuff, like, you know,
running up and down the
Oak Alley of the house
and that sort of thing.
So we were very blessed in how we
scheduled the movie for the character to...
for Tom to really get immersed in the
character.
And then when we finally got to the bench
in Savannah, which was actually a little
more than halfway through the schedule,
you know, Tom said, this is like...
He said, this is like taking a warm bath.
It's like, I'm so comfortable in this
character.
He was at a point where he got the
character, he narrated the entire movie,
and I shot every line of narration on film
because we were there for, I think,
three days, just doing him narrate,
doing the bench.
And, of course, those big shots and stuff.
But I knew that if we
didn't shoot every line on
film, it would sound
more read than performed.
It would sound narrated.
So he performed every line of narration.
And then after that, we just, you know,
completely powered through Forrest.
He just had it down for the rest of the
movie.
And then, of course,
those were all the heavy
scenes we had to do
came after we were done.
When we were on the stages here,
we were done on location.
I think the other thing that happened on
this movie as a process was whenever we
would try to force something, it would
never actually work out.
And we always had to allow the gump part
of it to come through.
And that even happened in the picking of
locations, because this location,
for instance, takes up two-thirds of the
movie.
And it just felt like this is where it
wanted to be.
And yet there was no park bench there,
and there was no place to sit.
So we just had to make that work.
Just as we finally found the place to
build Forrest's house, it was a place that
Bob could actually come and finally say,
you know, this is talking to me.
We wanted all of the early parts of
Forrest's childhood to almost seem like
they were out of a Norman Rockwell
illustration.
So we actually took colors and,
in fact, the outside of the school scene
that's coming up was taken literally from
a composition of his.
Looking at Sally Field now, I recall that
Bob saying that for the first,
you know, 20 minutes of the movie or so,
the whole movie will be riding on the
acting prowess of the mother of Forrest
Gump.
Not only is that going to continue until
she finally dies in the film, but it was
really critical to find a
very strong actress to
carry this film until Tom
Hanks came into the picture.
And Sally was certainly, you know,
an actress of stature that could carry it.
I always saw Sally in this part.
I don't know why.
You know, Wendy Finerman, the producer,
suggested her in, like, the first day or
first week that I, you know, signed on to
do the movie.
And it's just like, wow, yeah,
I was, you know, Sally.
And I sent Sally the script, and I was
very worried about it because,
you know, she has to play, you know,
ultimately Tom...
I mean, when you say it, it's not really
that way.
You say, Sally, why don't you play Tom
Hanks' mother?
But that's not what it really is.
She ages with makeup.
And so she read the
script, and she completely...
I mean, she was
signed on in a second.
She just completely got it.
Now, it's interesting that the character
of young Forrest came to us very
serendipitously in that this
young boy saw an open casting
call that was taking place, I
believe, in Memphis, Tennessee.
And he lived in northern
Mississippi, and his mom
encouraged him to go head
up and try out for the film.
Ellen Lewis, our casting director,
brought this tape out to us in Los Angeles.
And we were all... I mean, you had a big
smile on your face because you had just
seen this unique character that,
so far, you hadn't seen anywhere.
And so we invited a number of boys out
for... actually to read in front of the
camera because sometimes
these children will just
freeze up and won't
be able to perform at all.
So this young boy, Michael Humphreys,
I think is his name, you know, came out.
And he was as natural as ever.
He didn't have any fear at all.
All he wanted was a peanut butter sandwich
off the catering table.
This scene has in it...
this is that Rockwell sort
of point of view outside
the principal's office.
But I think there's an
element in this scene
that I've always loved,
which is this chart.
Because this was Bob's way of showing what
Forrest's IQ was.
And what's wonderful about this chart is
that if this didn't exist, if Forrest
didn't have an IQ that was below normal,
you couldn't tell this story.
In other words, Bob was able to isolate
this boy and this character as a simpleton
that had... and then you learn,
who has an innocence, that you're able to
take him through all the
events of the movie without
having a point of view that
would destroy these scenes.
The only reason he could have
an effect on the world that he
did is because of his innocence
and because of his simplicity.
We don't want to see anybody left behind.
And I think the other thing that was fun
about this was that even though Forrest
was supposed to be stupid, it was stupid
is as stupid does.
Because he really never did anything
stupid.
His heart always took him in the right
direction.
It always makes you wonder
how a kid like this can have
such a great understanding
of the humor in this scene.
The way this movie came
about was Wendy Finerman saw
an idea in this book that
she bought back in the 80s.
And whatever that was, that I don't know.
But when Eric Roth took the assignment to
adapt the book, and he was like the last
one in a string of writers, and I don't
even know how many went before him,
who weren't able to crack it, he saw
that the glue to the story was this...
the glue to the movie
was this love story.
And that was... so basically
it's Eric Roth's adaption
of the book is what
made this movie what it is.
That's like the tone.
And of course tone is the key thing,
and that's what you do as a director.
I don't know, there's no way that you can
explain it other than you just know it.
It's like the famous definition of
pornography.
I know it when I see it.
You just have to feel it.
You're just there in the set, you know,
that's not working, it's got to be like this.
You're doing that too self-consciously,
you've got to do that straighter,
the humor comes from the fact that you
don't understand you're being funny.
So we try... it's all inspired by the
screenplay, definitely.
It's inspired by the screenplay,
but then I think what the director does is
he has to hold on to it, and keep it from
falling off.
And of course the movies that are always
the ones that work the best are when
you're totally on the razor's edge with
that tone.
Because in a movie like this, I could have
fallen off the fence and it would have
been really corny and stupid,
or I would have fallen off
the other side and it would
have been really grotesque.
So it's like just that fine, fine line,
you know, and that of course is...
it's very nerve-wracking
when you're doing it.
It's just really hard.
There's something interesting about Elvis.
I mean, we worked with Peter Dobson on
Johnny Bago's series, and we knew that
Peter was an Elvis fan deep down in his
heart.
And he really knew his moves, and it was
perfect to play the young Elvis.
And then Bob also recalled that Kurt
Russell had done an Elvis movie,
in his youth, and had probably done the
best job of depicting Elvis on film.
So Bob recruited Kurt Russell to put the
voice in for Elvis in the film.
Some years later, that handsome young man
who they called the King, where he sung
too many songs, had himself a heart attack
or something.
Must be hard being a king.
You know, it's funny how you remember some
things, but some things you can't.
You do your very best now, Forrest.
I sure will, Mama.
I remember the bus ride on the first day
of school very well.
Are you coming along?
Mama said not to be taking rides from
strangers.
This is the bus to school.
I'm Forrest, Forrest Gump.
I'm Dorothy Harris.
Well, now we ain't strangers anymore.
Now, the sort of lyrical
way that this child
speaks, of course, is his
natural way of speaking.
And Tom was searching
for a voice for Forrest, and
when he heard this
young boy speak, it clicked.
And I think he matched that rhythm as the
older Forrest.
I can't sit here.
Now, I knew that this scene was going to
stay in the movie because Bob's son,
Tom's daughter, Don
Burgess' son and my nephew
were all on that bus and
all had speaking lines.
I do remember the first time I heard the
sweetest voice in the wide world.
You can sit here if you want.
I had never seen anything so beautiful in
my life.
She was like an angel.
Now, young Hannah had come from Colorado,
I believe.
I think she lived in Aspen.
And she hadn't ever worked in a film
before.
It's interesting that she had the same
unique sort of damaged interior in the way
she played the character that Robin brought
to the role, even though she was beautiful.
Mama says stupid is as stupid does.
I'm Jenny.
I'm Forrest, Forrest Gump.
From that day on, we was always together.
Jenny and me was like peas and carrots.
She taught me how to climb.
This tree was just right across the street
from the house, which was right across
from the farm where Jenny grew up,
as well as Vietnam.
Yeah, I think the breakthrough that you
had when you found Oak Alley was the place
where you set Forrest's house was that not
could we just shoot that section of the
movie where his house was and,
of course, where you found this beautiful
oak tree and Jenny's farm, but also the
whole Vietnam section could be shot just
going down a dirt road on the same
plantation.
And then also in nearby
Beaufort, we could stage
the other Vietnam
scenes and the shrimping.
And all of a sudden, this production,
which seemed incredibly unwieldy,
started to kind of come together in such a
way that you could shoot it all in one
place and base the company in one place,
but take the viewer all over the South.
And I think the other aspect is that we
never did anything with this Oak Alley.
We just let it stay as it was
over all the years, because this
was the deep-rooted part of
Forrest that never really changed.
It was his heart, even though everything
else changed.
And I love the fact that we actually didn't
apply any kind of embellishments or shtick.
And then this sequence here is really, I
just think, magical when I think about it.
Just seeing what actually happens with
these braces and how Forrest transforms.
A really great movie is a perfect blend of
truth and spectacle.
And when you can deliver spectacle on the
screen in terms of performance or action
or special effects or recreating ancient
Rome, whatever you're going to be doing,
and at the same time blend a story about
human truth.
If you look back on all your favorite
movies, those are the ones that work.
That's different than two
people in a room talking about
their emotional issues and
it's just completely boring.
So you can't do it without spectacle well,
and you can't just have spectacle.
So when you can blend the two,
if you look back in your own library of
movies that you like, I
would think that you'll
find that most of them
have that combination.
Now that's actually a running double.
After a while, Michael
Humphries didn't like to
run very much, so we
had to give him a little help.
He takes to running as though it were
learning.
You know how people say somebody took to
learning?
Right.
And this is a house that we built and
planted the whole field.
Yeah, the field must have
looked like how it looks at the
end of the movie when you
first arrived on the plantation.
Without any crop there at all.
Any greenery.
Right.
But this shack was there, wasn't it?
No.
Oh, you built the entire thing?
Yeah.
I thought there was a shape of a shack
there.
You're right, there was the shape of that
shack over somewhere and we brought it
over there and then we added the side to
it.
Right.
Kitty!
Come on!
Get.
back here, girl!
Where you at?
In order to make the movie, you know,
I think that you just have to,
you know, have a
compelling story and I look for
characters who have to
go through a character arc.
Because that's what, as I
was explaining earlier on,
that's what all those pivotal
characters in the movie do.
And I think that that's what, you know,
Western dramatic storytelling is about.
It's about characters who undergo a change
and therefore that character proves the
premise of your movie and then you know
what your movie's about.
And I think that whether we, you know,
whether it's done in a melodramatic way,
you know, where it's the old gunfighter
who hung up his guns but he's got to put
them on one more time to save the town,
you know.
Or whether it's a more subtle story that's
all about human emotions.
It's all about a character who has to,
you know, has to go through some sort of
test and undergo some sort of,
you know, character change.
And those are the ones that I find to be
the most compelling stories to make movies.
So I guess that's what I look for.
And I think if you look at all my movies,
you'll find it in there, even in the
comedies and even in what lies beneath,
you know.
I mean that, you know, it's like,
you know, for me I had to hang the whole
movie on whether or not Michelle Pfeiffer
was going to deny the truth or not,
you know.
And that to me, at least I know where the
movie's going to go when I have that.
It's interesting.
We had a much more elaborate
transition from Forrest as a
young boy to Forrest growing
up as the Tom Hanks character.
But Bob decided this was a much more
expeditious way of taking the audience,
you know, right into our story.
And I think he was right.
Now it used to be I ran to get where I was
going.
I never thought it would take me anywhere.
What I said to the sound team and to Alan
and the editors is that we should use the
records as if there was a radio on in
these scenes.
You know, because one of the things that
did happen, I don't know if it happens now
in your generation, but in my
generation, you know, I think
it's different now because
there's such a diversity of music.
But in my generation, everybody always
listened to the same music.
Everybody always had the same records.
You could go to any 16-year-old's
house and he would have
the exact same records as
every other 16-year-old in America.
It was just one of those phenomenon.
So we could use that as signposts to
history.
When Alan and I got together
and we said, okay, now
how are we going to do this
blend of score and records?
It came down to this wonderful kind of
template which is, Alan said, I'll
underscore all the emotion and the records
can play the landscape.
And that's what we did with the music.
The records play the action like when
Forrest is running and stuff like that.
And Alan comes in when,
you know, like Vietnam is
basically all scored by records
until the guys start dying.
Then Al starts, you know, sneaking in.
And so that's how we did the movie.
And when he's running across America,
it's all records.
So the records played the landscape as if
it was part of set design.
And then Alan just played all the
emotional underpinning of the characters.
We were just out there hanging out there.
I just had no idea that any of this would
work.
You know, when you get down on yourself,
it's all about how you look at everything.
You know, you could look at it,
it was all very melodramatic.
It was all very, you know, soap opera-ish.
There was no convention, storytelling
convention.
There were no bad guys.
There was no ticking time bomb or anything
in the movie to keep the plot going.
And I wasn't sure, you know, I wasn't
sure.
Now, after the fact, I understand that, you
know, Forrest was, you know, an innocent.
So what he said to everyone was always
presumed as the truth.
That's what makes his character work,
because, you know, he's like a baby.
So he has no agenda.
So you take what he says at face value,
which is what allows the story to work.
All the sequences that
were historic in context
required a tremendous
amount of research.
Because we reenacted these perfectly.
Which required finding cast
members that looked exactly
like the people who were
in the real-life footage.
And recreating portions of the event so it
looked like at one time you could be
watching the real event and
another one a recreation of
it and not be able to tell the
difference between the two.
In some cases we'd put Forrest into a real
event.
In other cases we would
reenact the same event and put
Forrest in it and you wouldn't
know which you were watching.
It was very clever and really,
really difficult.
Is that gunk?
No, that couldn't be.
Sure as hell was.
You know, I thought it was
kind of, I thought it was very
ironic that so many presidents
in my lifetime were shot at.
And, you know, when
you put them all together in
a two-hour movie, it's
actually pretty amazing.
Or, not all presidents, but, you know,
famous people and politicians and whatever.
So I thought that would be kind of a
humorous way and a black sort of way and a
dark sort of way to sort of just give us
these milestones in modern American history.
One of the things I think that I always
enjoyed about the movie also was that
being set in the South,
that so much of the history
of that period really
revolved around the South.
And so it was a real
journey through our time,
specifically our times with
a Southern perspective.
The other thing I think
that when I look out and see
these cars, I realize was
that these were our times.
So that we actually grew up, a lot of us,
during these times.
So when we were recreating
these scenes, or creating
the scenes, we were
recreating our own adolescences.
I understand why I love this movie.
I understand, I mean, even while we were
making it, I knew why I loved it.
Because I was recreating sections of my
own life.
And I really thought when
it was done that all of my
friends were going to love
it too, for the same reasons.
But I had no idea that
somebody who didn't live through
these times was going
to find this so fascinating.
But obviously, the character transcended
the time.
And it became, in a sense, a period movie
that happened to be our period.
Also, Forrest walked that
typer right in the middle, where
he never got hung up on
all the things that we all did.
So the rights and the wrongs that we might
have been defending...
He didn't have a perspective on them.
Forrest Gump, his heart just let him
through.
No, and once again, if he had had a
perspective on them, and had an opinion
when he got into a situation, then the
movie wouldn't have worked.
You couldn't have done
the scene with Wallace
if you didn't
misunderstand the situation.
And many of the scenes to come...
If he, in fact, didn't understand...
Bringing his innocence into all these
scenes is what makes them so effective.
And as I watch all these
scenes unfold, it's amazing
that every single scene
is a revelation to Forrest.
Nothing to him... He doesn't understand
anything in his life until he experiences it.
But I've just never seen someone
experience so much knowing so little.
Yeah, I think at this
part of the movie, you
still think you're much
smarter than him.
Yeah.
And by the end of the movie, he surpassed
you.
No, he actually has a
much greater understanding
of mankind and humanity
than I think any of us do.
And he knows himself.
Mm-hmm.
I sit next to them in my home economics
class all the time.
Now, Forrest is like a little boy in this
scene.
Uh-oh.
Oh, I'm sorry.
It's okay.
I'm sorry.
But the great thing that Bob always does
in scenes that are extremely sensitive...
is he takes the Mickey
off of them by having
just a little taste of
humor so that you can...
sort of...
you know, takes the pressure off of,
you know, the tenseness of the moment.
Like having the girl witness Forrest with
Jenny here in the dorm.
Mm-hmm.
No.
So this is really,
technologically, one of the
two breakthroughs on
Forrest Gump, I think.
Actually taking historic footage and
recreating it to tell a story...
and manipulating archival footage and
putting new words into the mouths of...
the historic characters was something, of
course, that had never been done before.
And I think it sort of opened up a whole
new Avenue in storytelling.
But basically the
process was that there's
a scene, okay, he's
going to meet Kennedy...
and then we had, you know, our two
post-production supervisors...
who started, I think, a year and a half
ahead of production or a year ahead...
and they just went to all
the archives all over the
country, in New York, all
over the place, Washington...
and they just, they had the guideline of
the script, the guideline of what I needed.
..
and they just came back with miles and
miles of film...
which they honed down to what they thought
was usable.
And then I looked at everything and,
you know, like for example...
when Kennedy's got
the football at the very
first shot, that was
actually in Rose Garden.
But we found that image
of him and we put him in the
Oval Office with our, you
know, background plate.
Stuff like that, so we just looked at
everything.
And then when we found the bits of film,
we went back, revised the script...
to try to weave the story into what we
had.
And I know the joke of, like, when Kennedy
says, I believe he said he has to go pee.
..
that was inspired by finding
this piece of footage where he
turned around in the Oval Office
and looked back at the camera.
And so we said, okay, that's where we
could put the punchline of a joke.
And then we figured out this whole peeing
thing which backed into that piece of film.
So it was a very complicated process,
constantly changing, going back and forth.
Hello, I'm Forrest, Forrest Gump.
Nobody gives a husky shit who you are,
puss ball!
You're not even low like scum-sucking
maggots!
Get your faggoty ass on the bus,
you're in the Army now!
Seat's taken.
Taken.
At first, it seemed like I made a mistake.
Seeing how it was only my induction day
and I was already getting yelled at.
Sit down if you want to.
I didn't know who I might meet or what
they might ask.
The narration worked like this.
There were obvious pieces of it that were
scripted very early on.
They were always in the script.
We recorded all the
narration that was scripted
ahead of time, before
we shot the movie.
And I had it with me
on a little cassette
player that I gave to
the script supervisor.
I had to build these pauses into the
scene.
Mama always had a way of explaining things
in between lines of dialogue.
I had to get a rough idea of how Tom was
going to do that.
I had those with me
and we tried our best
during the shooting to
build in those pauses.
Then, like I said, I had Tom perform on
film.
I was inspired by Amadeus.
What I loved about that movie was that it
was up until Forrest Gump, I always
thought it was the most beautifully
narrated movie.
Usually when you see a movie that's
narrated, it's an excuse for bad plotting.
But when I saw Amadeus,
what I loved about it is that you
would cut to the narrator to
react to the scene you just saw.
And I thought, now that works.
So I used that in Forrest Gump.
So I never knew what pieces of Tom I was
going to need on film when he was
narrating until I assembled the whole
movie.
So I shot it all, which did two things.
It gave me all the pieces and it allowed
me to have Tom perform the narration,
which is the way I wanted him to do it.
So we did all that, and
then we cut the movie
with all that film
narration that we had.
And then once we had to really start to
fine cut the movie and hone it all down,
then Tom went back again
and we wrote new narration,
linked scenes, take
things out, tighten things up.
Weave in and out of scenes.
There's a scene in there
where he's talking about Bubba's
mama not ever having to work
in anybody's kitchen anymore.
And the joke just wasn't working.
And in one of these takes, Tom just went
off and did an off-color joke on camera.
But in the setup, he looked at the other
actor and said, and you know what?
And then he told this really dirty joke.
So I took the and you know what out and I
dropped it in the movie.
And if you look at that
piece of film really, really
closely, Tom's a little bit
out of character in there.
So it was a lot of fun to ultimately edit.
So I was able to decide where
I was going to weave back
and where we were going
to come back to the narrator.
And a lot of times I come back to him
where, you know, he's just reacting or
he's going to start telling a story and
it's all...
And I cut back to him and he doesn't say
anything.
He just sort of is kind of winding up for
the next little chapter.
Hey, come.
Get a load of the tits on her.
Turns out, Jenny had
gotten into some trouble
over some photos of
her in her college sweater.
And she was thrown out of school.
But that wasn't a bad thing because a man
who owns a theater in Memphis,
Tennessee, saw those photos and offered
Jenny a job singing in a show.
The first chance I got, I took the bus up
to Memphis to see her perform in that show.
That was Amber.
Amber Flam.
Give her a big hand, guys.
Good job, Amber.
And now, for your listening and viewing
pleasure, direct from Hollywood,
California, our very own Beatnik Beauty.
I think it was an inspired
choice of a song to choose to
have Jenny singing as a
naked folk singer here in this...
Bobby Dillon.
Yeah, Bob Dylan.
...heroes must a man walk down before you
can call him a man.
Her idol was Joan Baez.
Right.
I don't know if the audience picked up
that Joan Baez pose during the dorm room
with that acoustic guitar leaning against
the wall.
That's a great shot.
I think when Robin had to learn to do the
few songs that she does play in the movie,
for some reason or another, I was called
on to give her guitar instructions.
Now, I think I can play about six or eight
chords on the guitar, but I can't play the
chords of the couple of songs she had to
play.
So, I taught her this and how to play the
song on the sidewalk.
Fuck!
Like you say, Forrest just follows his
heart everywhere he goes.
He just can't help himself.
And he always does the right thing as not
only a character, but a man.
And I think that's the part that was
really difficult because there was a lot
of questions in and around going to
Vietnam and the service and not going and
fighting the war and what made you a man
of that generation.
And Forrest just kind of was able to do
all the right things.
And right here, I mean, you know and you
just feel how much he really, really cares.
Now, this was on a bridge outside of
Savannah, wasn't it?
Where we shot this?
Yeah, and we put in all the lights in the
background for the club.
The exterior of the club.
The interior was back in Los Angeles.
The Jenny character, I thought,
sort of represented the unfulfilled,
the hole in the soul part of an American
generation of not being able to find
fulfillment in anything
other than sex, drugs,
rock and roll, whatever
was going on at the time.
And Forrest was, you
know, he was sort of this... he
represented the ideal of what
America was supposed to be.
Mom, God and apple pie, right?
And Jenny was the reciprocal of that in
her character.
So what you have is that wonderful unity
of opposites, kind of.
So you have two people
who are totally polarized
in their culture who are
romantically attracted.
That's great movie stuff.
I think for those of us who live through
these times, this is where it started to
really become very
personal and kick in the whole
idea of what it meant to
go to Vietnam in those days.
No, and of course, we all have our own
feelings about how we felt about the war.
And of course, Forrest is going to a place
that he doesn't have any idea about at all.
And so we're bringing
to the party all of
our own understanding
and feelings about it.
And once again, Forrest in his innocence
doesn't have any of those feelings.
I remember very early on, Bob was talking
about that scene with Mama there by the
river, hugging Forrest, and hearing this
Creedence Clearwater song.
And hearing the flapping of those helicopter
blades while he heard the song blaring.
And I think he could hear while he was
shooting the end of that scene,
he could hear them kicking him before he
came to this shot.
Now this terrified me when we shot it.
Because this was actually a tidal flat.
The water would come in, seep into this
area, and then drain out.
And of course, when we
shot in this area, we had to
pick the time of day when
the water wasn't there.
But in fact, what you
can't see is that that
helicopter isn't quite
touching the ground.
That helicopter pilot was able to bring
that helicopter in just above the ground
for our huge movie star to step off and
come into the scene.
And I said, oh God, when we had to do a
second take, my heart nearly dropped.
But this pilot, who had piloted
helicopters in Vietnam, hit the Mark
exactly right every single time he flew
that helicopter in.
You must be my FNG.
Morning, sir.
Get your hands down.
Do not salute me.
They're goddamn snipers.
Michael T.
Williamson was the actor.
He came in at an audition, and he read
with Tom.
And both Michael T., when
they came in, and when
Gary came in, they both
auditioned for the part.
As soon as I saw them, I knew they were
the guys.
And Michael T.
came up with the lip.
He did it.
He said, I want to have
this big, thick... what we
call them in the movie
business is called a plumper.
And so he had one built, and he put it in
there.
And when he showed it to me, I thought it
was great.
And then Gary came
up with that line, you
know, that you better
tuck that thing in line.
So we put all that stuff in there,
and it worked great.
And Michael T., when he was designing the
character, he always just wanted to have
that kind of lip hanging out and his mouth
open a lot like that.
So that was his.
I can't take credit for that.
Lieutenant Dan sure knew his stuff.
I felt real lucky he was my lieutenant.
He was from a long, great military
tradition.
Somebody in his family had fought and died
in every...
I think we shot these scenes on the last
day of shooting, didn't we?
That's right.
And some of the... on that rooftop.
Yeah, we recreated in little sandboxes all
the different forefathers of Gary Sinise's
character and shot
them all in succession on
the rooftop of a hotel
on Wilshire Boulevard.
Right.
Yeah, this is one of those
movies where you went from
thing to thing to thing, and
they were always different.
I think it was right next to where Jenny
was doing her suicide.
That's right.
One, take good care of your feet.
Two, try not to do anything stupid.
Lieutenant Dan was so difficult to cast,
in a sense, because we had to depict a
character who went through an incredible
transformation.
He had to be very hard
and not in touch with
himself and really harsh
on our main character.
And by the end of the movie, develops an
incredible understanding and compassion.
And had to have a lot of likability.
And so, Gary Sinise could embody all the
facets of this character.
And he had to be willing to let them take
his legs off.
Yeah, that's true.
You know, there were
some people who thought
we had cast a legless
person in that role.
And thought we had put fake legs on in the
other scene.
I was like, wow, that's really a stretch.
As I remember, Dale
Dye put these guys through
a whole boot camp to
get them ready, right?
Yeah, he did.
As a matter of fact, when we were casting
everybody who was to participate in this
scene, we warned them before they were
going to be cast in the movie that they
had to go attend this boot camp with this
real lieutenant, Dale Dye, who had served
in Vietnam and has become one of the
leading consultants in Army films.
And boy, I got to tell you, these actors
would come back to me with these harrowing
stories of their experience they had to
spend with Dale, because he wanted them to
really understand what it was like to be
an infantryman.
You know, he was firing real—you know,
he had real guns, and he was blowing
things up and making them sleep there
overnight and trying to scare them and
make them understand what it was really
like to be there.
Now, some of the actors loved it,
and others were terrified.
I've actually spoken to Vietnam veterans
who—and Dale Dye, actually, our consultant
on the film, who said that the terrain
that we found in South Carolina is the
closest to the terrain in Vietnam that he's
ever seen depicted in a motion picture.
It always makes you feel great when you
know that you haven't just created a
setting that doesn't look like the real
thing.
And also, in this area here, there were
actual water moccasins that had to be
cleared out before these guys went in
there.
Yeah, I think we put some
charges in there to wake
them up and scare them off,
didn't we, the day we shot?
That's right.
And also some chain-link down,
so they could walk in there.
And Tom Hanks was wearing protective
garment on his legs in case he got bitten.
They couldn't penetrate and actually bite
him in the leg.
Shoot, it even rained at night.
How you, Forrest?
Hey, Bubba.
I'm gonna lean up against you,
and you just lean right back against me.
This way we don't have to sleep with our
heads in the mud.
You know why we a good partnership,
Forrest?
One of the things that you begin to notice
here, actually, I think it's subconscious,
but Bob's choice to not ever show the
enemy.
Yeah, I remember when
we scouted the location
where the big battle
was going to take place.
I thought, what a brilliant idea to never
actually see the enemy there.
I think it's something that
Bob is very aware of, is how
to keep the intimacy of
the point of view of a scene.
So that you actually stay with the
characters, and you don't go outside of
whatever that space is that they would be
perceiving.
Yeah, I mean, we most recently worked on
Castaway, and when he did the plane crash,
he only allowed the
viewer to see that crash
from the point of view
of the main character.
And once again, when we witnessed this
terrifying gun battle that takes place in
Forrest Gump, since it's from his point of
view, it's even more terrifying,
because you don't know what the heck's
going on.
And the more you
actually know about the
situation, actually,
the less terrifying it is.
The other aspect is, this breaks the rule
entirely, because these are Forrest
telling the story about
Jenny, but they're
not things that he ever
actually could know.
So we see those throughout,
but that was one of the
ways that Jenny stayed
alive throughout the film.
Yeah, that was a rule that Bob broke,
his own point of view rule, which was
never to leave the point of view of his
main character, but it was the only way
that he could figure out to keep her going
throughout this movie.
And there's only a few times,
though, in the film that we
actually leave Forrest and
go and pick up Jenny's story.
This one shot, it's all one shot.
We had the infamous Dale Dye as our
military consultant.
I asked him, what would happen in Vietnam
when you were involved in these firefights?
And he said, it was just mass confusion.
He said, that's all, guys are just
screaming and there's stuff flying,
and it's just confusion.
And I said, well, that's what we have to
do.
And then the only other
thing I did was, I wanted
it to only be from
Forrest's point of view.
So in other words, you never cut to the VC
line in weight.
You just see muzzle flashes of their
weapons and things like that.
It's just all about these guys who just
stepped into hell.
So that was the idea of it, just to make
it crazy.
And so the sound went along with that.
This was one of those situations where we
had this chance to really do, and it's so
nice to do, this is one of the first movies
I did that was all digital like this.
So it's great to have
that spectacular low end
frequency stuff come in
and all these huge explosions.
But it was pretty much just layering this
wall of sound in the battle sequence.
It just went from this kind of...
You know, it's one of
those things where we were
just having a little bit
too much fun in Vietnam.
So it was time to bring in the ugliness,
and it worked pretty great.
I think here's where the score by Allen
starts to bring us into a level that just
becomes more and more throughout the movie
from here on out.
The first time I ever watched the movie
from beginning to end, I had Allen there.
I had Allen there, I had my
editor there, I had my assistants
there, and I had Randy
Tom, the sound designer there.
And just this handful of people,
we put the movie up on the...
Actually, this movie was edited on film.
This was the last movie I edited on film,
actually.
So we actually had film.
So we projected the movie
from beginning to end, and it
was like Allen went home
that night and started writing.
And it was interesting, because I put temp
music in when I show the movie to Allen.
You know, some of
his old stuff, or other
composers' stuff, just
to fill the scene out.
But when I ran the
movie for Allen, the whole
first scene with the
feather was silent.
And the only music that I put in were the
records when I ran it for Allen.
I didn't have any temp music in the movie
at all.
And he literally came
home on the synthesizer,
and he wrote that opening
theme like that night.
Because we were going out to a preview or
something, and I said, I can't think of
what to put in the beginning of this
movie.
And he went and he wrote it, and it was
something that he...
And we had this kind
of scratch track out of the
synthesizer that we previewed
with in our early previews.
So, you know, that
was one of those things
where the movie was
definitely talking to Allen.
I think this is some of his greatest work
that he had in the movie.
You know, he just went away, and I guess a
couple of months after I ran the movie for
him, I went up to where he lives up north,
and he just started playing me temp cues.
And it was just, you know, just sketches
on the piano.
And it was just great.
I mean, we didn't change a thing.
This guy is so complex, this Gary Sinise,
because he wants to die just so that he
can be a part of his own heritage, which
is that... He wants to die with dignity.
Well, and that he had a relative who died
in every war.
And he thought that his destiny was to die
in the war like his forefathers.
And he didn't want Forrest to,
you know, to interfere with that.
And here's where Forrest
is smart, and Captain
Dan is not, because
he knows how to survive.
I always thought it was
sort of like a Hitchcock
MacGuffin or something
that Forrest was dumb.
Because it's something that everybody
followed as though it were true,
but in fact, it actually had no real
meaning.
In the sense that I think he was actually
smart.
But see, his heart was true.
You hear the enemy here.
Now, this was very, very complicated,
the strafing by these planes.
It had to be shot in two parts.
One where we actually had Forrest or Tom
Hanks running, carrying Michael T.
And then we cleared everybody
out of the set and set off
these explosions here on
this island in South Carolina.
And then blended the two parts of the shot
together to look like he was actually
running through the scene with the real
explosions.
And isn't there a rig also helping him
carry, Bubba?
Yeah, we had an overhead crane that took
the weight of Michael T.
Off of Tom so that he could in fact appear
as if he was lifting him.
And got it set to a weight
that he could hold and it would
actually track with him so
he could run carrying Bubba.
And then of course we removed the wire
later.
You got shot.
Then Bubba said something I won't ever
forget.
I want to go home.
Bubba was my best good friend.
And even I know that ain't something you
can find just around the corner.
You want a cameraman who
understands the story, understands
the style of what it is that
you're doing with the camera.
And the big controversy that we had at the
beginning of the movie is when I announced
that I thought the movie should be made in
widescreen.
And everyone said, everyone meaning my
producers, my cameraman and my editor,
said widescreen?
This isn't Spartacus.
This is a story about this guy with a low
IQ.
And when I started talking about it with
Don and we started realizing that it was a
widescreen story because it was about a
guy who's running.
It's about a guy who kept going across the
screen.
The only thing that
wasn't compatible with the
format of the movie was
the Washington Monument.
And the Washington Monument probably isn't
compatible in 185 either.
But the movie laid out beautifully in
widescreen.
The thing that was great about it being an
intimate story in widescreen is that in
widescreen you can do close-ups that are
also over the shoulders at the same time.
So you get the power of
having both characters in the
same frame and you get to
get real close on the actors.
And as Don Burgess said to me, he said,
well here's the thing with widescreen.
He said the trade-off with widescreen is
every shot is really hard to compose.
It takes a lot of time and a lot of
effort.
But when you get it, just about every shot
is great.
And he was absolutely right.
You have to force yourself into really,
really doing the composition beautifully.
In.
the ping-pong scenes, they all look
natural.
But there's so much of Bob's trickery in
them.
And I think this is where his sense of
humor comes out.
It's also a testament to
Tom's abilities, not just as an
actor, but shows his talents
in so many different ways.
The way he could just pick up ping-pong.
I don't know if he played
ping-pong hardly at all in his life,
but just after no time at all,
he was playing like an expert.
I remember we were in the editing room and
we were playing with the three songs here
that make up this sequence, these
three-door songs.
And we tried all kinds
of different songs,
not thinking we should
have three-door songs.
But we just couldn't do any better than
the songs that Bob initially chose to
accompany Forrest becoming this great
ping-pong player.
Come and watch me play.
I played ping-pong so much, I even played
it in my sleep.
Now, you listen to me.
We all have a destiny.
Nothing just happens.
Gary understood that character.
I mean, he just absolutely immersed
himself.
He's like the metaphor for the crippled
part of America.
Like, you know, the America that got blood
on its hands.
The Vietnam America.
You know, his character has to confront
the fact that we were involved in this
illegal war of aggression and all this
stuff.
He speaks for America in that scene where
he says, this wasn't supposed to happen.
You know, this isn't how it was supposed
to ever happen.
So, you know, his character is probably
the one that makes the most spiritual
transformation, where he has to accept the
fate that was dealt to him, then he has to
go through this period of anger,
then he has to go through this period of
acceptance, and finally he has to,
you know, he has to grieve it,
and then he comes out okay on the other
side, which is an absolute spiritual journey.
See, I think that's the
next point of reference,
is that this wasn't
supposed to happen.
And that there was a plan that's gone
wrong.
Gone awry.
Yeah.
And I think that's how a lot of us,
you know, felt from that generation.
No matter what side of the war you were
on, this is where it starts to become
bigger than just about the Vietnam War or
the 60s.
And it's interesting that the two elements
that he finally talks about at the end of
the film is where we did feel like we had
a destiny.
But at the same time, we were floating
like feathers on a breeze.
And just whatever came
into our lives at that moment,
we allowed that to take
us down different paths.
But at the same time,
we had this inherent
feeling that, you know,
there was a purpose.
These two were in conflict with one
another and constantly are in the movie.
Guess what, Lieutenant Dine?
They want to give me a...
Ma'am.
What'd they do with Lieutenant Dine?
They sent him home.
Two weeks later, I left Vietnam.
The ceremony was kicked off.
Tinkering with historical footage is just
an extension of, you know, tinkering with
history, whether it's written or recorded
or whatever.
I mean, we didn't suggest that the original
footage that we used is no longer intact.
But, you know, I made a feature movie,
which is a fictional entertainment.
I mean, everybody knows that.
I think the ethical question comes mainly
to journalists.
And you've seen it happen in the last
couple of years in political campaigns
where politicians have been grafting
themselves into scenes with other,
you know, politicians or famous people
that they want to be associated with.
I think that's where the real ethical
question comes.
I think, you know, a movie is just a
movie.
Well, my favorite story, the one that I
like to tell, is that this question
probably came up when they invented the
printing press.
When they invented the printing press in,
you know, the 13th century or whatever it
was, and someone probably said,
hey, this is great, we can print the Bible.
And then somebody probably said, yeah,
we can also print lies with this thing.
This will be great.
So, you know, nobody believes what they
read in the newspaper, right?
So, that's just a common, you know,
everybody says, well, you know,
I'm not going to believe that just because
somebody wrote it.
Well, now you have to
just say, well, I'm not going
to believe that just because
that image is moving.
Just because an image is moving doesn't
mean it's truth anymore.
And that's just sadly what, you know, we
have to, sadly, or maybe it's a good thing.
It's probably good to question everything,
but you can create digitally a flawless,
perfect, moving lie.
And, you know, probably
somebody with the money somewhere
is going to do it, and it's
going to be a big scandal.
And then everyone will say,
oh, you know, just because I
saw that on the TV news
doesn't mean he really said that.
I had a couple of guys come up to me while
we were filming this scene here at the
Lincoln Memorial, and were from,
had gone to school at Columbia University
and had gone to a march that they thought
we were depicting here, and said this
looked and felt exactly as they remembered
it from the time.
And once again, that just
makes you feel so proud of
everything that went into stage
an event like this in a movie.
Of course, historically, this was a
demonstration that would have taken place
in our movie in the year 1968,
and there was not a demonstration in 1968.
It was 1967 and 1969.
Right, so we blended the
two events together and
created this one big
event that Forrest attended.
Right.
I remember at this time, I went to this
similar demonstration in San Francisco,
being on the West Coast.
And this actually resonated quite a bit
for me, because it really did feel like,
even though we were on the East Coast,
it felt like a very similar situation.
So, you know, when I came up from L.A.
to San Francisco and marched at Golden
Gate Park...
Can't hear you!
Can't hear anything!
This one!
Give me that!
Anytime we do anything with a special
effect, it's always storyboarded.
You know, but the thing about storyboards
that you have to be careful with is that
you have to have the storyboards, but
then you have to be able to revise them.
You can't just insist
that, you know, a lot of
directors say, it's got
to look exactly like this.
And then, of course, you know,
you physically can't do that sometimes.
But storyboards are important for communicating
an idea to a large amount of people.
Like, we storyboarded Vietnam.
We storyboarded anything that had to do
with a visual effect.
Because it's so much easier to say to,
like, 15 people, it's going to look
something like this,
rather than to, like, try to
explain the shot to people,
because everyone sees it.
We put a storyboard in
front of them and go, oh,
okay, okay, now we know
where you're getting at.
So that's what I use storyboards for.
I never storyboard, like, you know,
scenes between two actors or, like,
any of the scenes, like, with Tom and Gary
and his apartment or anything like that.
I would, you know, never
waste an artist's time to draw, you
know, coverage and over the
shoulders and things like that.
But whenever you have to do something that
you have an army of people that have to
work on the shot, it's a good idea to have
storyboards.
Being there and seeing
these actors, you know,
pull this stuff off
was really a lot of fun.
But I'm, like, one of these weird,
you know, I don't really have a lot of fun
when I'm making the movie, because it's
just, like, it's just too much hard work.
And the reason that,
you know, people will look
at movies and say, oh,
that must have been fun.
And you go, that was really not fun,
because the movie's fun to watch,
but the making of the movie was really,
really miserable for a lot of reasons.
And the main one was my ultimate vision
for everything is ultimately compromised.
And I think that that's what you have to
do as a filmmaker.
You have to just turn it over.
You have to give up.
Because in the morning you're going to the
set and you got this long list of 20
setups to do this sequence
really great and get all
the coverage you need and
have everything you need.
And then by lunch you
haven't gotten one single shot
yet, you know, and you
start crossing them all off.
And at the end of the day you've been able
to scramble and get four setups that you
can scrape the thing together and make it
work, you know.
And it's like, you
know, so it's like, damn,
you know, I could have
really done this better.
But everybody was too slow and it took too
long and they've...
And, you know, and something's always,
you know, it's like somebody didn't
realize that, oh, we didn't put gravel
over there.
So the camera truck got stuck and that
costs you an hour.
And it's like, oh, man, you know,
you know, there's like all these things
that really make making movies for me not
fun.
The fun part for me is in the editing room
because that's where I have the most fun
because it's just me and my film and my
editor.
And, you know, all the,
you know, the actual
shooting of a movie
is always just surviving.
Just getting through the
day and getting enough
in the can so you can
make it work somehow.
He doesn't mean it when he does things
like this, he doesn't.
I would never hurt you, Jenny.
I know you wouldn't, Forrest.
I'll tell you where the luxury came with
this movie is that, you know, and it's
been in all my movies, actually,
for the last 10 years, 15 years,
is that, you know, you get to a point
where you work with such good people,
both in the cast and in your crew,
that when you get in the editing room,
you don't have to do things like edit
around bad performances or they're
screwing up their lines or focus buzzes
and things like that because you do end up
at the end of the day with
really good film and your choices
can be made based on the
artistry of the performance.
You don't have to cut around, you know,
glitches.
So once you get to that point where you
can work with really professional people,
both in front and behind the camera,
you end up with pretty good film.
So once again, this is a series of shots
that take us through a journey that Jenny
went on, where Forrest wasn't there,
and the camera leaves Forrest in his point
of view in order to fill in Jenny's story
to the audience.
But it was the only way that Bob thought
that he could actually, you know,
keep you current with where her character
was going in the movie.
I didn't want it to end.
Wish you wouldn't go, Jenny.
I have to, Forrest.
Jenny?
Things got a little out of hand.
Just this war and that lying son of a
bitch Johnson.
I would never hurt you.
You know that.
You know what I think?
You should go home to Greenbow,
Alabama!
I think that's the only time in the movie
that Forrest actually shows his anger.
Mm-hmm.
Over this person that's actually
physically assaulted, Jenny.
That's so right.
See, you look at a scene like this and how
as an art director are you supposed to
comment on putting a bunch of buses around
and a giant hippie camp with tons of props
in the background as though that has any
real meaning?
And yet that's the only
thing that makes it different
than if you were a tourist
in Washington, D.C.
today as far as the staging.
But that's not something that you're
really even going to look at.
You absorb it.
But it's just to try to be a
natural way of saying that
you're in this time period
with those demonstrators.
And yet it's all just thrown away.
And rightfully so.
And just like that, she was gone.
Out of my life again.
And so after all this, what I thought was
interesting for me was to be able to not
only have the moon
landing but actually to sort of
reclaim the American flag
by putting it in the background.
It was interesting when we did this scene
that we actually had one of the leading,
I think, ping-pong players from Taiwan.
And this was a scene that we shot without
a ping-pong ball, in fact.
We just went through the motions of hitting
the ball and then put the ball in later.
But this guy, who's
one of the best players in
the world, couldn't hit
a ball that wasn't there.
Of course, none of us can, but he couldn't
even swing at a ball that wasn't there.
Now, I know, Rick, this
is a scene that's true to
your heart because I
think you are John Lennon.
Well, I'm a disciple.
And to be involved with a movie that had
John in it and to actually see that John
got his inspiration from Forrest for the
song Imagine...
Can you tell us what was China like?
In the land of China, people hardly got
nothing at all.
No possessions?
No, what's so wonderful is that there's
nothing sacred.
There's truly nothing sacred in this
movie.
And everything, the source of meaning for
everything can be tampered with,
manipulated and had fun with.
And that's really one of the charms of the
movie is you just don't stop at anything.
You can't hold anything too
close to your heart and think you
have the answers or the greatest
understanding for anything.
Because there's always some shading of it
that maybe you didn't look at.
Lieutenant Dian!
They gave you.
Well, the key to working with the editor
is you got to get an editor who you really
enjoy being with, who you respect,
you have to have mutual respect.
And you can't be in an antagonistic
situation with your editor like,
you know, that is the worst.
Because editing is true collaboration when
it really works great.
You know, the whole thing about making
movies is collaborating.
But it really, really comes focused in the
editing room where you have to,
you know, you have to let the editor take
your film and try it.
And then be open-minded and say,
well, that, you know, the way you put that
together isn't the way I intended it,
but it works pretty good.
Or that you have to say, no, you know, I
try it the way I, you know, envisioned it.
My editor works from day one of shooting.
He's editing.
I don't look at it, but he's there cutting
because, you know, there always comes that
moment where you got to like
maybe see something and see
how the movie's coming
together to see where you are.
So my endless
conversation with my editor in
dailies is, oh, you know,
don't throw that out.
Don't use that.
That's never going to work.
You know, it's like just cut it all out.
But there's also that's conversation one.
And then the other conversation I'm always
having with my editor is, oh, I'm glad,
I'm glad you explained that to
me because I didn't understand
what I was supposed to
do with this film, you know.
So it's like, you know, you're
shooting all this stuff and
he's like collecting, how's
this supposed to go together?
So, you know, you kind of like walk him
through it.
And then the real
editing comes, you know,
when you have to finally
form the final movie.
And that's when you need that sounding
board and that second, you know,
and you need somebody and you really need
somebody who looks at the film objectively.
The director's downfall is having the
inability to kill his darlings.
You know, you do this great big remote
headshot with all the stuff, you got it
all in one, you know, and you're so proud
and everything, everybody hits their marks
and everything's in focus and everybody's
great.
And the editor says, it's boring.
You know, I'm going to need an insert to
cut this thing in half.
So, you know, you got to have somebody
who's objective enough to be able to,
you know, to help you collaborate,
make the movie as best as you can.
I have to help myself.
Now, if I accept Jesus
into my heart, I'll get
to walk beside him in
the kingdom of heaven.
Did you hear what I said?
Walk beside him in the kingdom of heaven.
Well, kiss my crippled ass.
God is listening.
What a crock of shit.
I'm going to heaven, Lieutenant Dane.
The cinematography and the way this movie
is being shot is...
I think it's deceptively simple,
but I think that it emotionally just felt
right and it created this sort of rhythm
of storytelling that allows you to
actually go from scene
to scene and always just
feel like you're focusing
on the right thing.
Bob moves the camera a lot
when he shoots his movies,
but he's always moving it
toward the focus of the scene.
And so that's why it always feels natural,
because you're always watching what you
want to watch, because he directs your eye
to what you should be watching.
And that seems simple, but it's in fact
very, very difficult.
I defy anyone to try it.
And I think Don Burgess gets it so well
that it's like a wonderful shorthand to
watch between the two of them sometimes in
terms of how they find the honesty of the
scene and exactly
where they want to have
the camera to tell the
story at that moment.
And it's a real collaboration between the
two of them.
You choose a cinematographer by looking at
his work and looking at his artistry and
how he's able to light and how he's able
to compose.
You look at that first.
Then the other thing you have to do is,
again, interview someone and make sure
that their personality is like
the same type of personality,
someone you're going to
be able to collaborate with.
I love working with Don because he really
likes to prepare.
I'll tell you a perfect example of the
genius of Don Burgess is that when we
built the house and we went out to the
location where we were on the river in
South Carolina and Rick Carter,
my production designer, had the house kind
of like with these sticks, like he put up
these posts just to give us a sense of the
shape of the house, the scale of what it
was going to be and he did it with
basically stakes and tape and he showed us
where the house was going to be.
On the river where he wanted it.
So we were there like staking this house
out like in March of the year that we were
going to shoot and Don pulled out the GPS
and he pulled out the compass and he said,
well, when are we going to be shooting
here?
And we said, well, we're going to be
shooting here at the end of April,
first two weeks of September.
And he said, I think we should tilt the
house about 20 degrees like that.
What that allowed is it allowed for the
sun to just hit the house absolutely
perfectly on the weeks
that we were there to
shoot the house and
make it look so beautiful.
So, you know, that's like a cameraman
who's really working and showing up and
working on the movie
and not just showing up on
the day and saying, is
this day or night today?
You know, if you ever have
a cameraman who shows up
on the day and says, is
this day or is this night?
You know, you got the wrong cameraman
because he hasn't been reading the script.
What's your problem?
Did you lose your pack in a war or
something?
Or is your friend stupid or something?
What did you say?
Is your friend stupid or something?
Don't call him stupid!
Hey, don't you punch her!
Yeah, shut up!
Don't you ever call him stupid!
Get the hell out of here!
Get your goddamn clothes!
Go on!
Get out of here!
Of course, just to reinforce the
difficulty of shooting a shot with a man
who has legs but in the movie doesn't,
Bob had to put obstacles in the set to
make it look even more difficult to do
such a thing.
But you don't even think about it.
And that's the part that I think is
interesting and almost magical is the
suspension of disbelief that you don't
want to know.
And I think that when film spaces create
that space where you don't want to know
anything other than what you're watching
and you're not drawn to see anything but
the story and the
characters, that's when movies
take on the most magical
elements that they have.
And I think that they touch us the most
deeply.
But that's not to say that the other
things don't matter.
You have to accomplish those in order to
create that illusion.
He didn't want to be called crippled, just
like I didn't want to be called stupid.
Happy New Year, Gump.
The U.S.
ping-pong team met with President Nixon
today at an Oval Office ceremony.
And wouldn't you know it, a
few months later, they invited
me and the ping-pong
team to visit the White House.
Now this is, for me, emotionally
where when I... I could
have gotten hung up in Vietnam
and the post-Vietnam syndrome.
But then to be kind of yanked out of it
into Watergate and actually get to go to
the Watergate Hotel to find the place
where you could actually view the break-in.
I know the much nicer hotel.
It's brand new, very modern.
We were actually able, in that unique
place in the movie, to tell a part of
history that people have never seen
before.
But to walk into that hotel room
and say, somebody could have
been watching this and to
know the implications of it later.
I love that.
Good night.
Therefore, I shall resign...
Again, the use of the television and the
media to move ahead in time and in space.
...to be sworn in as President at that
hour in this office.
I think Bob enjoys, in these sequences,
moving in and out of the public perception
and back to the personal as a way of kind
of defining how a lot of us perceive the
disparity between what our social lives
are and what we really think on the inside.
And just like that, my service in the
United States Army was over.
So I went home.
You know, there's something about the
Gothic South that we depict in the movie
that, you know, the South is, in a strange
way, the most sort of patriotic,
you know, segment of America in that it's
slow to change and it's, you know,
the South, as far as I was concerned,
was something that was always in the
script and in the place that it always had
to be set.
And it's where these characters came from.
I mean, it was like that
was, you know, those
are the guys who fought
in the war in Vietnam.
That's where, you know,
characters like Jenny,
you know, left and
traveled around the world.
And I think that the thing that the South
does more than anything is it evokes,
I mean, the one constant that we had in
the movie that worked really well
emotionally was the idea that characters
kept coming home.
And the South has
that going for it, I think,
more than any other
region of the nation.
You get the sense that it's constant.
You know, those oak trees are 150,
200 years old.
You know, so that was like one of the
things that was great about the South
being the place where it's set,
because it does give you that sense of
coming home to something that doesn't
change when the world around does.
But that sort of stays constant.
I remember everything you said,
and I got it all figured out.
I'm taking the $24,562.47 that I got.
Well, let's laugh.
After a new haircut and a new suit,
I took mom out to a real fancy dinner,
and I bought a bus ticket and three Dr.
Peppers.
Tell me something.
This sequence always fascinated me.
If you actually look at it, not just for
the emotional quality, which is,
I think, wonderful, but
where we go as we cut
away and how we tell
this part of the story.
Again, you know, just the staging is very
simple, but later on in the movie,
we're going to be by the tree with Jenny,
but there we were still knowing that we're
in the South because of the Spanish moss
and the old oak trees.
You know, one of the great things of
working on movies like this is not just
taking a trip down memory Lane,
if you will, or being able to re-examine,
you know, the sort of our recent past,
you know, our own lives, but you get to
learn so much about so many unique things
in the world, like, for example,
shrimping.
You know, I came into this movie, I didn't
know the first thing about shrimping.
And experiences like that, when you make
movies, open up to you and present a whole
new world, you know, that you really
wouldn't have known existed.
You ever think about naming a boat?
It's bad luck to have a boat without a
name.
I'd never named a boat before,
but there was only one I could think of.
The most beautiful name in the wide world.
Again, here we're now into the full
throttle of the cocaine 70s.
I.
hadn't heard from Jenny in a long while,
but I thought about her a lot.
And I hope that whatever she was doing
made her happy.
I think Don Burgess did a wonderful job
here.
If you notice the color palette he's
dealing with, and how you really can
almost feel the harshness
of the drug, and what
that's leading this
character to experience.
Yeah, I think if I recall, he changed the
color palette to a much cooler,
sort of blue-green color palette,
and really desaturated it.
So it made you sort of feel all the lack
of warmth and, you know, anything of that
nature in the scenes that make you feel
like everything's been drained out of her
life, just like he did with his color
palette.
You know, it's just amazing
how far you can stray
from the path, but you
can still come back home.
And, you know, it's staggering to think
how much experimentation and, you know,
wanderlust exists in so many people's
lives, certainly mine, and I think a lot
of people of our generation, you know,
before they can find, you know,
come back to the things that have the most
meaning.
And this movie certainly, through the
character of Jenny and the character of
Lieutenant Dan, takes you into some of the
most, you know, harrowing experiences that
you think are what you should be
experiencing.
And you need to experience those in order
to discover what really does have meaning.
Now, I remember when Bob presented us with
this dilemma on this day.
We went and scouted this location and he
said, yeah, I'm going to stage this
reunion between Lieutenant
Dan and Forrest and he's going to
crawl up onto this pier and
it's going to be exhilarating.
But, you know, what would really be great
is, unbeknownst to Forrest, who's jumped
off of his boat with no one
navigating it, what if it crashes
into the pier and he's kind of in
the background and it blows up?
Now, this was like on a Friday and I think
we had to shoot it either in a day or two.
So, we somehow had to pull that gag
together.
Get that pier out
there, for one thing, and
make it sure that it
would detonate on cue.
And also not hurt the boat when it
actually crashes into it.
And that the boat would stop in time not
to actually run aground.
I told you, if you were ever a shrimp boat
captain, that I'd be your first mate.
Well, here I am.
I am a man of my word.
Now, in those days you did that the
old-fashioned way.
For real.
I like to compare this
whole debate, I guess, or
question about digital
effects to the microphone.
You know, nobody says,
gosh, you know, there
was probably a microphone
there the whole time.
You know, there was.
Nobody talks about it anymore,
you know.
But 70 years ago, that was like what
everybody talked about.
What do you think the microphone was?
Was it in the flower pot?
Was it in the thing?
Because that was the new tail wagging the
dog.
And so, there'll be some new thing that
everybody's obsessed about and worried about.
And the idea that you'll be able to change
the tie, or even not, you know,
change the inflection of an actor's
performance.
Or change the way he might, you know,
edit.
You could probably edit lines in and out
of his mouth without there being a problem.
You'll probably be
able to do that with your
editing package in
another couple of years.
And no one will question it because it'll
just be another tool.
So, the trick, of course, to all this
stuff is to make it invisible.
To make all technique invisible.
The reason people say that is because,
you know, you can't see the effects is
because we weren't creating alien
landscapes.
We weren't creating weird creatures.
And that's when people say, oh,
that's an effect.
But what we did is, you know,
we would change the sky and
we would put birds in and
we would do things like that.
And that just makes the movie better,
I think.
But those are all, you know, it's the same
technology that you use to do creatures.
So, you know, the trick is to take all
this digital imagery and make it as
invisible of a tool as, you know,
the long lens is.
Now me, I was scared.
But Lieutenant Dan, he was mad.
Come on!
It's going to take a force of God to
strike Lieutenant Dan down.
That's right.
This is all or nothing.
Now here's a good example of saving a lot
of money.
Because that's stock footage.
And now this is back into what we created.
And in fact, there was a hurricane that
blew through there and there were still
minor remnants of that hurricane that we
used as a backdrop to shoot that scene.
That's right.
And this digital thing is going to happen
once it becomes cheaper and once you can
move faster because, you know,
time is money.
So it's all about the money.
You know, at the end of the day,
you know, it doesn't really matter.
I mean, if this movie,
exactly this way, with all these
characters were shot on 8mm,
it would be just as compelling.
It wouldn't be technically as beautiful,
but it would be just as compelling.
So the thing about
whatever the format of the
moving images has never
been of any consequence.
It's all about the script.
It's all about the script and the story.
And, you know, the technical
stuff is always changing
and it's always just
going to be there as a tool.
So, you know, whatever's going to happen
is going to happen and the audience will
accept... they'll tell us
what they like to see.
...in my time, but that tops them all.
We were sitting next to a millionaire.
Well, I thought it
was a very lovely story
and you tell it so well
with such enthusiasm.
Would you like to see what Lieutenant Dan
looks like?
Yes, I would.
That's him right there.
And let me tell you something about
Lieutenant Dan.
Forrest,
I never thanked you for saving my life.
Forrest obviously never changes.
He's this guy who
just, you know, wanders
through life telling
the truth as he sees it.
And everybody around
him, you know, has to...
everyone's lives around
him are touched in a way.
The dynamic starts to
disintegrate like a house of cards
because, you know, he
calls everybody on their stuff.
So, you know, everybody around
him changes and some people,
you know, are destroyed
like Bubba, you know, they die.
But, you know, Forrest just goes through.
So the two pivotal characters in the movie
for me are the Jenny character and the
Lieutenant Dan character
which are, you know,
and they represent sort
of like the human growth.
They're like a metaphor for, you know,
emotional growth in any human being,
you know, where you have
to go through these different
stages of different pain to
come out better on the other end.
Where's Mama?
She's upstairs.
Hi, Forrest.
I'll see you tomorrow.
We sure got you straightened out,
didn't we, boy?
I don't like any improv when the camera's
rolling because, you know, I don't like to
watch actors on the screen thinking up
lines.
When we're working things out,
when we're in what I call rehearsal,
which are just these large table readings
with the cast.
And when we're blocking the scene out,
if an actor wants to try something or he
has an idea and we can make it work or I
think it's right, you know, we'll design
it into the scene and we'll write it down
because, you know, it's just not fair to
other actors for actors to start saying
lines that, you know, and it's not fair to
the camera operator or
anybody who's working,
you know, because they
don't know what to do.
So I like to have
everything scripted out, but
that doesn't mean that
things can't be changed.
And I never would beat up on an actor,
you know, to say the words specifically
unless it was crucial to the plot or the
character.
So if an actor wants to change words that
are easier for him to say, as long as the
intention of the line is correct and
doesn't destroy, you know, the most...
You know, if the actor wants to cut out
the key plot word of the entire movie,
you know, we're not going to let him do
that.
But what a director basically does, I don't
like to put my actors in psychotherapy.
I think what they want
a director to do is just
tell them how the character
is feeling in the scene.
And where they go for that, you don't have
to tell them, now remember when your dog
died when you were six years old and how
sad you were?
They don't need to hear all that.
They just want to know, well, you know,
this is like, you're really sad here.
And then they go off and they find that.
And then, you know, then you're like the
throttle, not that sad.
And you have to like just, you know,
keep their performance in perspective so
that, you know, they're not going to be
playing the character, you know,
over the top in the beginning of the
movie.
You're not going to save something for the
end.
That's what a director, I think,
does in regards to talking to actors.
Just talk about the character's feelings
at the time.
At this point, as he starts saying all the
things that he's been, you realize
somebody must have been actually putting
all of this together.
And all that documentary
footage and everything that we
came in and out of all of
this in a very simple manner.
And so the editing process
here is something that I
think is worth noting just
because you can't see it.
And the rest is just for showing off.
So I gave a whole bunch of it to the Four
Square Gospel Church.
But really, that all comes down to the
script.
I mean, it was so cleverly
scripted that, you know,
that the pieces fell together
so seemingly so naturally.
But I think it's something that Artie
Schmidt in particular brings to the mix,
which is having a sense of
exactly what the right thing
to do is in relationship to
the story that Bob's telling.
And so that he's like an anchor.
I cut that grass for free.
But at night time, when there was nothing
to do and the house was all empty,
I'd always think of Jenny.
And then, she was there.
Robin brought so much
to this character that you
really could feel the
distance she's traveled.
Hello, Forrest.
Hello, Jenny.
And the authenticity, I think,
of her character.
Yeah, there's no doubt that in casting
her, you really had to find someone who,
deep inside of themselves,
could show the emotion
of a damaged and truly
deeply hurt individual.
And Robin somehow was able to depict that
throughout the entire movie.
That somehow beneath the surface of her
beauty was this hurt in herself.
And she was the only
person that we actually
read for the character
of Jenny for the movie.
She came and screen
tested with Tom and everybody
came back to a meeting
and Bob said, she's the one.
Casting that character was over.
I just think she approached
it from a very real deep
place and she wasn't
sentimental about it at all.
This really was what her life had been.
And it really came through, I think.
In a lot of ways, Lieutenant Dan and Jenny
were similar.
In that they had these
very... these destinies
that they thought
they needed to fulfill.
I mean, I think that Lieutenant Dan was
more... thought he was more aware of what
his destiny was and Jenny was searching
for her.
But at the same time,
they had to explore to the
greatest extreme something
in order to heal themselves.
In a way, though, being, I guess,
damaged to start off with, trying to just
go like the feather was not the answer for
her.
And just the way trying
to stick with a preordained
destiny was not
Lieutenant Dan's answer.
So they were like flip sides of the same
coin, I think.
And this part, you know, is the healing
that could take place, you know, at home.
This is them creating a home.
And again, Bob's choice of where to be in
order to tell this part of the story.
When to be intimate, and
yet when to take a step back,
and yet maybe you're even
more intimate because of that.
I don't know if I have a favorite
particular shot.
It's probably something
that's pretty simple and doesn't
involve any special
effect or anything like that.
But I guess my favorite shots,
if I were to answer the question perfectly
honestly, are the ones that are completely
invisible.
You know, to me, those are the ones that
I'm always the most proud of.
If you say, oh, what a great shot,
then I haven't done my job really that
well because you were able to see the
shot.
And that means that I've jarred you out of
the experience of seeing the movie,
and I've sort of hung a
little flag on the movie
and said, don't forget,
there's a director here.
So, you know, the ones that
I'm the most proud of and the
ones that work the best are
the ones that you can't see.
You would, Forrest.
But you won't marry me.
You don't want to marry me.
Why don't you love me, Jenny?
I'm not a smart man.
But I know what love is.
Just like earlier you were
talking about where Don and
Bob decide to place the
camera in telling the story.
And here, at a very intimate moment,
the camera starts here with them.
But just like in the scene where they're
dancing, just a little bit earlier,
they decide to move the
camera outside and let them have
this moment, this very intimate
moment, together themselves,
or by themselves.
What are you running off to?
I'm not running.
They actually decided at this section of
the movie to have absolute silence.
And I think the audience needs it.
They need silence to feel this pain or
these few moments with Forrest.
That day, for no particular reason,
I decided to go for a little run.
So I ran to the end of the road.
And when I got there, I thought maybe I'd
run to the end of town.
just run across Greenbow County.
And I figured since
I'd run this far, maybe
I'd just run across the
great state of Alabama.
And that's what I did.
I ran clear across Alabama.
For no particular reason, I just kept on
going.
The running sequence was
really the most complicated
sequence to incorporate
to shooting this movie.
Because we had to create a timeline for
Forrest taking this extraordinary run,
criss-crossing the country a number of
times.
And he went through a whole evolution of
his hair and makeup and wardrobe and found
characters along the way that followed
him.
And we shot these completely out of order.
Whenever, in fact, we had the opportunity,
we would shoot a running shot.
And you'd just refer to this very
elaborate booklet that would tell you what
he looked like and who was with him at the
time.
So, you just ran!
Well, the largest challenge in this movie
was how many sets we had to open.
I mean, we had, I forget the number now,
I think it was in the 70s.
I think the two biggest challenges were
opening a new set every day.
Because that meant you had to go into
something new, you had to light it.
You had a whole new
group of atmosphere
people, you had a whole
new group of costumes.
We had so many different periods of time
that the movie wove through.
That was hard.
And the other thing that was hard was
designing the run at the end.
In terms of beard continuity and
disintegration of clothes continuity.
And where we were going
to be able to shoot and
how we were going to
put those pieces together.
That was an absolute nightmare because
there was no form to that.
And that was something
where we just went and
shot forests and the
photo double and whatever.
It was running across America,
but we couldn't just do it in real time.
So, it was a real...
that to me, I remember
that very... that was
really hard to design.
Because I knew I couldn't switch those
shots around later.
I couldn't say, oh, this shot should go
later because this beard would be too short.
We're running for women's rights.
Or for the environment.
Or for animals.
They just couldn't believe
that somebody would
do all that running for
no particular reason.
Why are you doing this?
I just felt like running.
It's you.
I can't believe it's really you.
For some reason when I was doing the same
beard...
It's interesting that all the
historic characters that we've
had in the movie has now
sort of turned around on itself.
And the main character in our movie has
become as famous in our story as the
characters in the scenes that we were
re-enacting.
Whether the presidents or John Lennon.
And so he's almost gotten as big in a
sense as all these other famous people.
I guess at this point
in the movie, it's like
he's incorporated all
of them into him, too.
So as you're watching, that's why you can
feel what he's added up to.
And then to have these scenes thrown in,
I think is fantastic.
Yeah, I remember when
Bob called me in and had
me read these two
scenes that he had written.
Both this happy face and shit happens
joke.
I read them and I said, these are the
darndest things, Bob.
And he said, you've got to be kidding me.
I said, oh no, we've got to have these
scenes.
And my God, this is just what the audience
needs at this moment in the movie.
Well, this is what it all adds up to.
Philosophically, that's where we are.
Somebody lost all his money in the t-shirt
business.
He wanted to put my face on a t-shirt,
but he couldn't draw that well.
And he didn't have a camera.
I love the justification, the rationale as
to how this happened.
Because he couldn't draw that well and
didn't have a camera.
But he wanted to put his face on it.
Some years later, I found out that that
man did come up with an idea for a t-shirt.
He made a lot of money off of it.
Anyway, like I was saying, I had a lot of
company.
My mom always said, you've got to put the
past behind you before you can move on.
In a sense, by incorporating all these
experiences in Forrest's life into where
he is today, and what we've all
experienced in this movie so far,
is propelling us directly ahead to this
moment on the bench when he discovers
that, in fact, he's within running distance
or walking distance of his destiny.
And it's kind of like the momentum of the
movie is carrying us to that point where
we're now going to take off in real time
with him.
But what's also true to Forrest is that
just when it's at its most serious,
it also means that the entire story you've
heard until now did not have to happen
because he didn't have to be waiting for
that bus at all.
So, you just were in the hands of an
idiot.
Now what are we supposed to do?
And just like that, my running days was
over.
So I went home to Alabama.
Moments ago, at 2.25 P.M.
as President Reagan was leaving the...
I think when we got
the first screenplay for
the movie, in fact, the
film ended on the bench.
And it was strange.
It was almost like waiting for Godot,
where you spent this entire movie on this
bench, and then at the
end, how do you end this
movie where there's
somebody just sitting there?
And Bob came up with
this breakthrough of actually
propelling us into real time
to tell the end of the story.
And I think that that was key to taking
this movie to a new level.
The original script that Eric wrote was all
narrated, and it was all after the fact.
And then the idea came about, and I really
don't remember how, of the narration
catching up to real time, and then the
movie taking on a life of its own.
And the only dilemma was we couldn't
figure out how to do the one line when
Jenny dies, which is you
died on a Tuesday or whatever
he says, because that was
just such an important line.
So we just ended up doing it, and we
rolled it into his scene at the graveside,
and that became that one line which we
were able to save.
So it was an important idea that the
narration stopped and we caught up to the
real film, and it ended up working great
for the movie.
It's a very simple place that she has,
but I like that it's in keeping with her.
And the scene here is just so touching.
I ran a long way for a long time.
It's so wonderful that they were
connected, so closely connected during
this run, where he was trying
to run because he couldn't
understand or deal with
the pain of losing Jenny.
There she was watching his run, and really
Forrest was in her mind all the time.
And of course the two of them were separate
from one another and didn't know that.
And there's the introduction of someone
who people recognize.
Yeah, little Haley Osment was a young boy
at that time, had never been in a movie,
and I cast him as young Forrest.
He was an intelligent
actor then, and of course
he's gone on to become
a young movie star.
His name's Forrest.
Like me.
I named him after his daddy.
He got a daddy named Forrest?
He got a daddy named Forrest too?
You're his daddy, Forrest.
Forrest, look at me.
Look at me, Forrest.
There's nothing you need to do,
okay?
You didn't do anything wrong.
Okay?
Isn't he beautiful?
He's the most beautiful thing I've ever
seen.
But...
is he smart?
He's very smart.
He's one of the smartest in his class.
Yeah, it's okay.
Go talk to him.
What do you want, Shane?
Partnering.
Forrest...
I'm sick.
What, do you have a cough due to cold?
I have some kind of virus.
And the doctors don't...
they don't know what it
is, and there isn't anything
they can do about it.
You could come home with me.
Jenny, you and little Forrest could come
stay at my house in Greenbow.
I'll take care of you if you're sick.
Would you marry me, Forrest?
Forrest, it's time to start.
Nancy Haig, the set decorator in
this film... I say in this film, almost...
because it was like she was in the film.
She just kind of permeated all the
settings.
She just seemed to really know the right
level to bring to all the environments.
Whether it's this wedding, or the last
scene in the apartment, the house.
I think she just did so
much research in the
area, and lived, in
a sense, in the area.
And everything that she did, that Nancy
did in the movie, seemed so naturalistic.
Lieutenant Day.
Hello, Forrest.
You got new legs.
New legs!
Yeah, I got new legs.
Custom made.
Titanium alloy.
It's what they use on the space shuttle.
For Lieutenant Day to now come around...
and you realize that he's now in the
position that Forrest was...
in relationship to his legs, at this
setting.
I think the structure of the story...
how it resolves the different storylines
of the other characters...
is incredible, because they all kind of
fold into Forrest, ultimately.
And even just looking at this scene,
where the wedding takes place...
and it's just a few intimate friends.
He's a very famous person, actually.
But it's just an intimate moment.
There's a very magical shot in the film,
sort of depicting time passing.
And the three of them finally together as
a family.
Hey.
Hey, Forrest.
Were you scared in Vietnam?
Yes.
Why?
I don't know.
Sometimes it would stop raining long
enough for the stars to come out.
And then it was nice.
It was like just before the sun goes to
bed down on the bayou.
There was over a million sparkles on the
water.
Like that mountain lake that was so clear,
Jenny.
It looked like there were two
skyscrapers...
A lot of the magical shots that you see in
the movie, like when Forrest is
reminiscing... to
Jenny, were real.
And they're depicted in the way that we
were blessed when we went to film them.
In a certain way, the experience of making
the movie was really blessed.
Because we really could
have had insurmountable
problems in trying
to tell a story like this.
But I felt that by the end of this
process, everything went right.
Everything would show up to a setting.
I was just so thrilled about the material
that we would get.
We would go to Monument Valley and we'd
have the beautiful sunset.
Or wherever we went.
The characters that we got to be in the
movie.
It's truly remarkable how
some movies just seem
to fall together, fall
into place just right.
And I had that house of your father
bulldozed to the ground.
When I really think about it, what I found
compelling about the story was...
it was this story about all different
types of love.
It was love between friends, between
mother and son, son and mother.
Romantic love, friendship.
And grieving.
It had all this great stuff in there.
Which is why I think the film was very
popular.
It's kind of a good thing and a bad thing
to think about it.
The bad thing is that we
have to go to movie theaters
to get in touch with grief
in our society nowadays.
But it's a good thing because people can
do that.
And I think that's what attracted a huge
audience to the movie.
When the movie was done,
we thought, well, no one
under the age of 35 is going
to understand this movie.
Before we released it, we said,
this is all about people who are the baby
boom generation, the Vietnam War,
the hippie peace movement.
And then all of America came to see the
movie, which was great.
So then we figured, well, no one in the
international market is going to get this
movie because it's all about American
history.
And it's got American colloquial humor in
it.
And then it became this huge movie all
over the world.
So it must have touched some nerve that's
beyond the historical part of America.
And it was all about, I
guess, the real human story
and all the life metaphors
that are in the film.
You know, I.
don't know if Mama was right or if it's
Lieutenant Dan.
I don't know if we each
have a destiny or if we're all
just floating around
accidentally like on a breeze.
But I think maybe it's both.
Maybe both is happening at the same time.
I miss you, Jimmy.
If there's anything you need, I won't be
far away.
Here's your bus.
Okay.
The good news is if we
ever do the sequel to Forrest
Gump, Haley's turned
into this big star actor now.
When he was that little and that young,
he was a great actor.
He just always had the fire, so it was fun
to see him go.
And Hannah, too.
Little Hannah.
She just showed up in The Virgin Suicides.
I love to see these young actors mature
and become good adult actors.
I want to tell you I love you.
I love you, too, Daddy.
I'll be right here when you get back.
You understand this is the bus to the
school now, don't you?
Of course.
The new one drove to yours tonight in
Forrest Gump.
You know, I think there's a real comfort
to having these bookends on a movie.
You know, where you start,
get to see this feather float
down and begin the story
and place you in this fable.
And then at the end, you brought so much
in your experience that it's wonderful to
allow you just to begin to think about the
journey with the feather.
The feather sort of closing the book for
you.
So many filmmakers constantly work because
they never want to deal with the letdown.
But you always go through withdrawal when
you finish a project.
Especially when it's something
where everyone is a joy
to work with and everyone
is doing such great work.
And where the emptiness comes from is that
all this passion goes away.
You know, it's like everyone was so
passionate about this movie.
And you want that with you all the time.
I mean, if you talk to people who knew me,
I mean, after this, I mean, the year after
this movie was done, I went into a,
you know, severe depression.
And it's funny, everyone thought, oh,
it's because it's so successful, right?
Naturally, you're depressed.
And it wasn't.
It had nothing to do with the success of
the movie.
It was about, you know, it was just about
being depressed because, you know,
this wonderful experience in your
professional life was over.
That's the good news and the bad news
about making movies.
They end.
They always end.
You're always going to be done with them.
And, you know, that's nice
because at least you're not
in one of those jobs like Jack
Lemmon in The Apartment.
You know, where, you know, your job never
ends and you don't know what it is and you
just keep moving a piece of paper from
here to there, you know.
But the price you pay for doing these
projects that actually must be finished is
that you have to then
deal with the emptiness that
comes along with it being,
you know, being over.
And, you know, everybody deals with it a
different way.
I personally, you know, now choose to go
through that letdown period and not sign
on for another project because I know that
I wouldn't be... I would be reacting to
the wrong thing and I would end up doing a
project that wasn't good.
I would be choosing the project for the
wrong reason rather than having a clear
mind and saying this is what I'd like to
do.
I'd be choosing a project to do as a
reaction to the one I was just finishing.
So my advice is, is to just deal with it
and know that it's going to happen.
You're going to have these, you know,
and what happens is when you're doing a,
when you're doing a, you know,
a giant feature film, it literally comes
to a screeching halt in less than 12
hours.
I mean, for the two years you're making
this movie, through the marketing,
through the advertising, through the
publicity, through the release schedule,
you're running in front
of this locomotive and
you've got a call sheet
that's as long as your arm.
And the day that movie opens, nobody needs
you for anything.
It happens in 12 hours.
Boom.
That's it.
Your agent calls you and says,
hey, did you see the grosses?
And that's the only call you get because
the movie's over.
So you've done your job and it just comes
to a screeching, screeching halt.
And you have to like, you have to learn
to, you know, you have to learn to live
with that because, you know, it just
completely is over.